so just to summarize of it one of the
distinctions I want to make is what what
then do the different models have to say
about this question or hypothesis of
moving beyond dialectical thinking and
so one of the limitations i think of
these models is that so we have current
models and then we have the hypothetical
territory that we would like to look in
and i think one of the if I had to make
a short list of what we could look to
advance is that in the current models
for example you'll hear a lot about
subject-object ships so there would be
Kagan statement that the subject of the
previous level becomes the object of the
subject of the next level but nowhere in
these models does the question of rise
for example is what is it for an object
for example to be for a subject and
that's a much more Eastern question so
the model is inherently limited by the
conventional assumptions of what a
subject and object are and so when you
start to move into this territory and
say well let me get underneath this
assumption and ask a question is what is
it for an object to be an object for a
subject then the whole foundation of
what my inquiry is becomes much more
complicate
um also for example we're looking at in
the current models of ego development
and how the ego makes meaning but we
have really don't ask the question or
incorporate into these models what is
ego in the first place we just assume
there's an assumption that we are
studying something that is identifiable
and has a certain Western meaning but
that we've not delve into the question
the model is not subject to the question
what is ego okay these I think kind of
questions move us to exploring new
territory there's this aspect that I
mentioned early of complexification or
sophistication of reasoning up toward
principles but there's no mention or
study of this move in the other
direction which is to deeper ontological
we could call them principles but the
word principle seems to only mean higher
and more complex or deeper ontological
point principles they're in a sense can
be simpler in a way we're more
foundational and so there's this whole
direction of awareness that is not
studied in conventional models
conventional or current models have
expressed a lot of when describes a lot
around this issue of polarity but the in
my opinion the ultimate polarity that
hasn't been looked at is the figure
ground relation
which we'll talk about in a subsequent
video but I believe that this is the
foundational polarity for all the other
polarities in it in there's some mention
of figure ground reversals but it's not
something that moves in any of these
developmental models and I think that if
these developmental models could see
that this could move then they would
advance into new territory there is
obviously in a corporate bration of the
developmental processes but there is no
attempt to rigorously tie these into
evolutionary ones and then even when
there's the mention of evolution and it
might my opinion that's not while
rigorous there's certainly no attempt to
look at involution Airy processes and
we're even the case of looking at for
incorporating into the inquiry of
symbolic representation is brought in
there certainly not much discussion
about non symbolic representation now
the word representation is probably
problematic here or so we might say non
symbolic presentation of self let's say
now what would drive what could possibly
drive development beyond these stages if
not polarity because we're saying that
polarity is dialectic and dualistic and
the new stages won't be driven by that
so what would drive development beyond
to even paleri itself and so we can look
this at this from the skills and task
models and they actually themselves
offer this and that is when you look at
task complexity and you look at skill
capacity there in many cases what is
seen is that the modern world presents a
problem like this that skills and tasks
are not growing at the same rate and so
during this era the skill capacity grew
faster than the task so we saw progress
and we could solve problems but in the
modern era currently yes we have crises
because the skills even at a meta meta
meta or cross paradigmatic or systems of
principles level problems are not going
to not being solved the problems are
more complex than these highest levels
can solve
and if it keeps going like that this
point of crisis will become a
catastrophe so even the people who are
working on developmental models in this
skill set inquiry have pointed out this
problem in terms of the negotiation of
polarities we will look at in the next
video which is kind of a feature video
presentation that the moving to the two
highest levels creates an option but to
different kinds of responses in both of
them are problematic because it creates
a crisis of ego and a interest in ego
transcendence and in terms of the
dialectical process of development in
outline by facetious so this was mostly
Fisher the Pope Gloria Gloria and the
fishes
one of the problems is that the
paradoxes that drive the dialectical if
eventually become apparent in recursive
and so those people enter into the
higher stages of trying to understand
and negotiate polarities and so these
are three crises that signify the end of
development in this trajectory and the
potential of development toward a
completely new trajectory driven by
these three very serious problems one is
a kind of an empirical world
problem-solving capacity that is lacking
one is a just a reasoning capability or
explanation problem-solving is lacking
and that brings us into actually crisis
of personal individuals in a crisis of
meaning